Hi, when we studied the motion graph paper we were trying to align two different point clouds
and to do this we had an optimization function that basically says that we were trying to find
the minimal distance between two point clouds if you did rotate and translate one of the point
workloads and that minimization functions had a closed form solution that we could use directly
and that's what we did in the in the study but I've never tried to actually derive those functions
myself to see how you get from that minimization problem to the optimized closed form solutions
so let's try to see how we could compute this so the first thing I will do so I will just define
a bunch of symbols that will be needed for SimPy and when we start from the minimization problem
this one is a vector is xyz points and points xyz also so I will rewrite the square distance
formula with the actual formula for the translate we have here and basically what you will do is
you have a function that basically says the first point x because now I have x y
and z so x y is minus the x prime y multiplied by the cossiness of the
angle plus the z prime multiplied by the sinus plus x zeros and the same for the
z is multiplied cossiness minus x multiplied by the sinus. I remove the y's
because when I'm trying to do a minimization problem here, I'm only
rotating and translating alongs x and z, so the y will be constant, so no
matter what the values will be for theta x0 and z0, y will always be the same, so
it's useless inside of my minimization problem. And now because we're taking the
square, the square distance, basically it means that I could just leave the
functions as this, otherwise I would have to do the square roots of these to get
the distance but then v squared would be square root squared and I don't need to deal with
it.
So I could just do this formula and that's what you have now in terms of x0, x is x i,
x prime i and so on and so on.
Has been rearranged to get rid of the parenthesis automatically by sin pi.
Now when you try to do a minimization problem of a function, what you do, especially if
you have square functions, you could just take the derivative of your functions and
look where the gradient will be zero, because that will be your minimum.
And so we will do exactly the same thing here.
I will take the partial derivatives of my functions in respect to theta and that gives
me that big function here and I take the partial derivative in respect to x0 and z0 and I
get all those two here.
Now from those functions what you do as I said you put them equal to 0 and I will expand
them so I will propagate the sums all over the place. So I get the first
functions equal zero, the second and the third equal zeros. What I have now is a
bunch of sums where I can see that I have also a bunch of constants inside of
those sums. So I will try to factor those terms and if I factor those terms
now I have to multiply by a bunch of stuff equal zero to multiply by a bunch
of stuff equals zero. I can get rid of those two because two x equals zero means x equals
zero. The two is useless. So I can get rid of all those twos. And I get now this with
all the constants outside x zero because zero with the sums. And we could see that we have
a lot of sums that are looking always the same. I get the sum of y, z prime i, same
it's already here, the same with a yxi. And inside of the paper they already
replaced those sums of yixi by xbar and I will do that same substitution here
because it would make it more readable and it would be making the life for
SimPy a bit easier to solve. So I get the xbar, zbar, xprimebar, zprimebar
define at this one, I can do that substitution inside of my three functions.
Now those start to look a bit more simple and what we can see is that the
first one still depends on x, z and theta, while the second one only depends on
x0 and theta and the third one only on z0 and theta. So I will try to solve those
to for x and z so I will be able to start to do substitution inside of the
other one so I'll solve x for x0 and I'll solve for z0 and if I do this I
basically have x0s equal x bar minus x prime bar cos theta minus z prime bar
sin theta and it's actually these functions we actually found x0s the
same way they've found it here and we found z zeros the same way they found set zeros here.
Now because I have x zero and z zero only depending on theta, what I can do is I take
my x zero and I'll replace it inside of the first functions and do the same for the z zero
all over the place and if I do that substitution and then expand everything
luckily enough a lot of parameters get cancelled out and you have this big
functions and now it's on your functions of the synus and cossinus data and more
importantly it's actually a polynomial where you could see that every term is
either a term multiplied by cossinus or synus so it's something multiplied by
synus by cossinus by cossinus synus so all of them is always multiplied either
by cosinus or sinus. So I can try to rearrange these functions and collect for the sinus
and cosinus terms. And what you end up with is something broken up. And what you end up with
is something, a big functions multiplied by sinus theta and a big parenthesis multiplied by
by Cosinus theta.
Now, basically, I have A Sinus A,
Sinus theta plus B Cosinus theta,
which is equal to zero,
which means that with a bunch of rearrangement,
you can end up with A Sinus equal minus B Cosinus,
and then Sinus divided by Cosinus equal minus B
divided by A.
And you finally end up with theta equal r tangent
of minus B divided by A.
So minus b divided by a.
And if I do this, so minus a divided by b here,
you get this formula, which is actually what they have here.
It's the same functions for the theta we have solved.
So now we have theta x0 and z0 as a closed form
solutions in the same way the paper did.
So this is how you derived those functions.
Hope you liked it.
It was a short one.
See you next time.